Hey guys, Shan this side welcome back to
the channel and in the previous video of
API gateway we have already seen how to
perform a routing and how to do the load
balancing and today let's see how we can
do authentication circuit breaker retry
rate limiting etc within an API gateway
so let's start without wasting any
further time so to understand this we
need to understand filters in API
gateway very important so filters can
intercept and modify the HTTP request
and response as they passes through the
gateway. Okay. So there are two types of
filter. One is global filter. Another is
root specific filter. Sometime uh
engineers also call it gateway filters.
So what are global filters? As the name
says apply to every request that goes
through gateway. Every. Okay. And very
good example could be of like performing
authentication. You want to do logging.
So those are some of the very good use
cases for the global filters. And root
specific filters are like as the name
says again apply to specific requests
that matches a particular route. Okay,
we will not apply them globally to all
the traffic. No only particular traffic
which matches a particular route.
Okay. And very good example would be you
can say or you use case would be rate
limiting circuit breaker resilience
retry that if you have multiple
microservices
you want different different
configuration for for this circuit
breaker configuration could be different
for this circuit breaker configuration
could be different okay I don't want to
apply globally to all my to all the
roots okay
so we will see that but for now just
have this definition like uh basic
understanding and later on it will get
more clarified.
So before we proceed further on the
global filters and root specific filters
this flow we need to understand
properly. Okay this is the overall flow
when a request comes to API gateway and
its complete life cycle. So now let's
say the client
hit the request
localhost 8083
/ products /1. So this is our 8083 is
our API gateway port number. The request
first goes to dispatcher handlet
dispatcher handler. Okay. After that it
pass it to route mapping handler. So
what route mapping handler do is it
based on this route / products it looks
in our application.properties properties
we define the routes right route zero
route one so route zero is for product
route one is for orders and some certain
configuration so based on the route
let's say / products it define which
config to use like I so
uh client hit / products right so it
would use
/ product/est
so it would use this route route zero
okay so it will create a route object.
After that there could be one there
could be many global filters. For each
global filter a prefilter logic will run
after that it invokes the next next
filter in the chain. So that you can
consider this as a chain of filters.
Okay. So first the pref filter logic you
can say that pre-logic runs after that
it invokes the next filter. So the next
filter of global filter will get
invoked. If there are no more global
filters it will invoke the
root specific filters. Again there can
be many root specific filters and for
each filter there could be pre-logic and
post logic. So first it runs the
pre-logic and after running the
pre-logic it invokes the next filter in
the chain. So again the next filter
could be root or next filter could be
your again global filter also. So now
what happen in this
there is a one global filter called root
to request URL filter.
What it will do is whatever the path we
are getting let's say / product / one we
have to create a proper endpoint right
callable endpoint because we are
invoking it with the
API gateway uh URL right localhost 80083
and based on this root we have to create
a endpoint so currently our URI is load
balancer so internally it has to call
service discovery then it do load
balancing and then take out a one
particular instance. So that is all done
by by this filter which is a global
filter and then this ultimately pass to
another global filter which is neti
routing filter. It task is to actually
invoke the micros service and finally
the micros service return the response
and this neti routing filter which is a
global filter it goes back to the
root specific filter okay and from there
it will run it's the post filter logic
so understand from this you have a
pre-logic
then you have like next and then post
logic. So this is the same code. Okay.
So pre-logic run then in the next it
invokes another filter that task is
completed. It control goes back here and
then it runs the post logic. So the same
thing. Okay. So it control goes back and
then it run the post filter logic. So if
you have multiple root specific filters.
So now all their post filter logic will
run. After that when all finish
it the control goes back to the global
filter this one and from there it will
now run its post filter logic. Okay.
After that all this finish
it runs one global filter at last which
is netty writer response filter. Its
task is to forward the response to the
client.
Okay. So this is the overall flow.
So now here one question should have
come to your mind is that hey
sh I see that global filters are before
the root specific filter also and global
filters are after the root specific
filter like why there is no no sequence
right. So I if I understand correctly
either it should be like all global
filters first global filters and then
root specific filters or all root
specific filters and then global
filters. Why there is a mix? Why global
filters are before and after the root
specific filter? What's the logic? So
the answer for that is ordering
in API gateway.
Each filter whether it's a global or
root specific is given an order.
Okay. The maximum the minimum the order
value means higher priority. Maximum
order value means low priority. For
example, if any filter has value minus1
and any filter has order value zero,
then filter with order value minus1 will
run before filter with order value zero.
Okay. So generally
most of the global filters are given
lower value than root specific filters.
Okay. So that's why global filters
generally runs before the root specific
filters. They are given lower value.
But some global filters like root to
request URL filter, native routing
filters intentionally given higher value
so that they execute last.
Okay. So if you see the order value for
these two global filters the order value
is given very high.
So
for root to request the order value
which is given is 10,000 and for native
routing filter so that this should
because this has to invoke the microser
right so it has to be like after all the
filters so that's why it gives lowest
precedence lowest precedence means
maximum value
okay so it has the lowest precedence so
means it should run last so its value
would be very high order value would be
very
So that's why
these two global filters comes very late
in the filter chain. Okay. And generally
global filters order values are smaller
than root specific filters. So generally
it runs
before the root specific filters. Okay.
So there are just like certain scenarios
where for specific filters I want to run
at last itself and now if you see the
order value of native write response
filter it's very less so means it this
filter will be executed first in the
chain okay so
so here if you see this is the filter
native write response filter let me zoom
it a
Okay, I hope it is visible. So here if
you see for the native right response
filter order is minus one. And if you
see
it's pre-f filter is empty nothing in
pre-f filter. So means it directly
invoke the next it directly invoke the
next filter in the chain and then it has
lot of code
into its post operation. So generally
what happening here is
so when the request comes here so you
can say that when the request actually
comes here it also passes through. So
actual if you see that it also passes
through this but there is no in
prefilter logic there is nothing okay so
it just pass to the next filter in the
chain and but during response
in the post filter logic it has lot of
logic and the logic is to
pass the return the value to the client.
Okay. So that's why its order value is
minus1. So that it will execute early in
the filter chain.
Okay. So that during response its post
operation
post operation or you can say that post
logic execute at last. Okay. Because
it's going in the reverse direction. So
the early filter its post operation will
execute at last. And why it want to
execute at last? Because we need to send
the response to the client. So it should
be the last operation.
Okay. So I hope this flow is clear and
why some global filters are before root
specific and why some are uh after that
is clear because this is very important
ordering.
Okay. And one more thing is what are the
by default values. So for global filters
if we do not define the order by default
value is that the lowest precedence.
Lowest precedence means uh it would be
executed last.
Okay.
And for the root specific filters. So
let's say you have created three root
specific filter. So what it will do is
it will just use index 0 1 2 like this.
So you have three root specific filter.
Right? So for the first filter root
specific filter order would be zero for
the next one it would be one and then
two likewise it goes. So this is the
default behavior.
Okay. So I hope till this point of time
we are clear what is global filter what
is root specific filter at least. Okay.
and the basic flow
like how the basic flows in a API
gateway happens
and yes for sure about ordering
now let's goes to the global filter
first
we know that
there are so many already pre-existing
global filters present like
root to return URL filter this is a
global filter I I already told you what
its task is. Native routing filter. It
task is to invoke. So this is also a
global filter. It's applied to all the
requests no matter what. Similarly,
native writer response filter. This is
also a global filter. It task is to
uh return the value to the client, send
the response to the client. So there are
already so many global filters. But what
it takes to write our own custom global
filter? Let's say I want to do it for
authentication
like JWT.
Okay. And I want it for my all requests.
So that's why I want to put do this
authentication into the global filters.
I want it applicable for all the
requests. So see
so J I created one class JWT O global
filter annotated with add the component
because I want to get it managed by
spring boot implements global filter and
ordered I told you that every filter
whether it's a root root specific or
whether it's a global filter
it's ordered like order value is given
If we don't give it by default it would
be given. Okay. Because we want control
like okay authentication should be run
before authentication should be run
before any other filter in the chain. So
that's why I want the control so that I
will give the order. Okay. So I need to
implement global filter and also the
ordered. So here if you see in the
ordered one
I give minus one lower value means
higher priority. So it would be it would
be run early in the filter chain I give
some negative number. Okay.
Now in the global filter we have to
override this filter method. Now in this
exchange this exchange represent the
request and response and this chain is
like the filter chain a filters chain of
filters. Okay. So first now this is all
our JWT
token
verification logic. Okay.
So I have take out a path exchange.get
get request get URI get path I got a
path if the path is / I don't want to do
any verification because this is the
time when user has to create the token
and a uh API gateway do not create token
it only verifies it for creation of the
token responsibility should be some one
of the microservers okay so if the
endpoint is / it just call the next
filter in the chain pass through. Okay.
But
if this is not the endpoint then for
rest all other request I want to
validate the token. So from the request
header I take out the authorization
header. If authorization header is null
means token is missing. So I'm saying
unauthorized.
Else I take out the token
from the header. authorization header.
Now your verification logic will come
here. So I have already created JWT
authentication video. Okay. Uh in the
spring boot series if you haven't watch
out kindly check it out because how to
verify how to create the token how to
verify the token I have already
discussed in there one. Okay. So your
verify JWT token logic will come at this
place. Let's say if the verification
fails then the exception it will catch
and we will say unauthorized. So
response I will set unauthorized and I
will mark the complete.
Okay, I will not proceed further. I will
make it request complete.
But if the token is valid then I am
doing chain dot filter exchange. So
means I am passing the request further
in the chain. to the next filter in the
chain. Okay. Now here if you see I also
added the post filter. So you have a
pref filter
prefilter logic. So what is my pre-f
filter logic here? This before chain
before I pass the request to the next
filter in the chain. Everything is my
prefilter.
Then at this point of time I pass the
request to
next filter.
Okay. After that I need a post logic. So
this is how we write a post logic. Okay.
So then mono do from runnable and inside
this this is an you can say that an
executable. So the your all the logic
whatever the post operation logic you
want put it inside this one. Okay don't
worry about this mono from runnable this
is actually a spring cloud gateway
internally uses reactive programming.
Okay and we will see that into when we
will start with the spring web flux.
Okay so just understand that for now uh
so that we have certain basic what
exactly happen here.
chain.filter exchange do not pass the
request to the next filter
synchronously. No, it passed the request
asynchronously.
And when it pass the request
asynchronously,
okay, and if you write the post filter,
it will automatically get executed.
It will not even wait for the chain to
complete properly micros service to get
execute and when the response come then
only post will get executed right it
will not wait since it is in a
synchronous internally do a
synchronously it will directly goes to
the post and completed and move ahead so
that's where so we just put then mono
from runnable we are saying that
once this asynchronous is completed
Okay. And when the response comes then
only perform this post filter logic.
Don't do it now.
Okay.
So this is our global filter. This is
how we write it. Very very simple.
Nothing else like
you just have to provide an order. You
have to implement global filter. And in
this filter method write your pre-logic
filter logic. call the next filter in
the chain and then write your post
logic.
Okay. And in the pre-logic I am doing
the authentication
here.
Okay. Do check out W uh JWT
authentication. You will get clarified
how this verify JWT token logic need to
be. Okay. It's very very simple. So I
don't want to do it now otherwise uh it
would like uh go into totally what I
have covered here.
Okay. Then the next is root specific
filters.
There are many pre-existing root
specific filters available in
SpringCloud gateway like add request
header used to add a header to the
request. Add response header used to add
a header to the response. remove request
header, remove response header like it's
to remove a request header and used to
remove a response header respectively.
Retry used to retry the request on
failure. We already have a filter for
this
request rate limiter used to apply rate
limiting. We already again see we
already have a pre-existing root
specific filter for circuit breaker also
we have it but how to use it now I'm
going to tell you.
So
see how it works. So now we are using
pre-existing root filters and later on
we will create our custom root specific
filter.
So now see this is my
product service root. Okay root0 and for
this only I need to def for this root
only for this root for this products
root only I want to define the filter.
Okay. So I'm defining filter. Now let's
see what is happening.
So I am so the just one example for the
pre-existing. So one of the pre-existing
is remove
request header. Remove request header.
So I how I am doing is
spring.cloud.gateway.root0.
So root0 means I want for this product
services for root zero. Right? So the
same dot filter zero. See I told you
there can be many filters, many root
specific filters. There can be many
global filters. So filter zero, filter
one, filter two, there can be many
filters. So this is filter zero, this is
filter one, this is filter two. So
currently I'm writing filter zero.
What is the name? Remove request header.
So this is the name. What filter? So
this is already present. This class is
already present. This filter class is
already present. So we are you can say
that we are giving a class name
and then
there is something called if this
required certain configuration
dynamic configuration okay certain
fields are there we where we can define
dynamic values so generally it given
like this spring.cloud.gateway
root0 filter zero dot ars dot name. So
understand now with this. So if you see
the framework
you will see a class remove request
header gateway filter factory. So we
just gateway filter factory you can say
that is get appended.
Okay. And before that whatever it is
that is our actual class name we give in
the application.properties properties it
automatically append gateway filter
factory while doing the mapping. Okay,
we we don't have to give this gateway
filter factory.
So if you open the class remove request
header gateway filter factory this will
get open. So name is clear like what
name we have to give. Okay. Second thing
if you see this
in this class
it extend
a abstract gateway filter factory and
there we have defined one not we this
framework has defined one config name
config. So if you see the name config
it has one
field name.
So that field value what is the value?
We can add it here. We can define it
like this. Okay. Dot args argument dot
ask dot this field name name
whatever the field name
we want to give. So see
this filter task is to remove the
header. So it required a name. What
header name I have to remove? which
header give me the name then only I can
remove right so I need certain input
dynamically through configuration
so that's why this configurations
is mainly used to define fields which
value we can configure it dynamically
through configuration so whatever the
name I can provide through configuration
like this root0 filter0
okay for this filter I'm working on this
filter right and This filter
uses this config.
Okay. So, and this config value has only
name. So, that's why name and I provided
this. So, what happen is inside this
apply
it uses this config name config. Now if
you see what it does from exchange it
takes out the request it take out the
header and it remove this name whatever
we have provided. So it's a dynamic
whatever the value we will give in the
configuration that will get removed
and then it goes to the next filter
chain.
Okay. So this is just one example. Don't
worry we will see more like it will get
clarifies how the root specific filter
works. Now let's see an example with
multiple root specific filters like
currently I showed one. So let's say I
want two three filters. So see I have
filter zero.
Okay
add request header. I want to add a
header. So
first thing when you want a header
definitely it required let's say name
and value. So header has two thing what
is the header name? What is the value?
So
if you see the name so these are all
pre-existing we are talking about okay
we are not creating any class now we
have just used this configuration. We
are just using this filters root
specific filters in our config.
So I am applying this add a request
header. Now the filter name is dot name
add request header. So what is the class
name might be present add request header
gateway filter factory. So if you see
you will see this class present into the
framework. So this in framework this
class is present.
Now here if you see this class is using
this config name value config. So it has
two parameter name and value. Now we
need to dynamically uh tell the value
right? What is the name of the header?
What is the value? Okay. And then we can
add it through config. So same thing
root0 filter zero dot ars. Now with this
dot ask means we have we are going to
assign value to its field. The first
field is name give the header name and
then dot value give the value. Similarly
for the response header.
Okay. So what is the name of the
response header? Add response header. If
you go in the framework you will see add
response header. So here if you see if I
search add response header gateway
filter factory. Okay.
So what is the config? It takes name
value config and name value config is
name and value.
So the same thing
filter one. So now this is my filter one
ars.name name. This is in the response.
Add this header name and the value add
this.
Okay.
Similarly, remove we have already seen
you want to remove a particular header
from a request. It only require a name.
So only one field.
Now if you see the hitter request and
see the response
response header. So in the response
header
you see this it got added X test
response header API gateway response. So
this is the header name this is the
header value got appended.
Okay. So these are all the filters which
already exist. We just want to use it.
Similarly retry root specific filter
also exist. How to use it? Let's see. So
again I am applying this uh retry filter
onto our root0 which is for product
service.
So spring.cloud.gateway root0.tf
filter0. So this is the first filter I
am writing for this root name I have
given is retry. Now you know what is the
uh class name you will find into the
framework. Retry gateway filter factory.
So this is get appended automatically
gateway filter factory. So if you open
this class you will see what
configuration it uses retry config.
Retry config has multiple values. Some
of them are like number of retries on
which methods you want to retry on what
status what should be the status when
you want to retry.
So I we have to provide values. So now I
am providing the values.
Spring.cloud.gateway
root0 filter zero. Now ours means in
this configuration whatever the config
this class uses in that it this get
mapped.
So it has one field retries. So retries
I am sending four time it should retry
methods this field
it should get retry for get and delete.
So only these two I have set. So what
would happen is
for get and delete requests whenever
there is a failure
a retry will happen. So four means total
attempt is
four one is original call
and after that three retry.
So total four. Okay.
Now we will do the testing. So in the
product micros service controllers I
have done like this just for testing
purpose.
Okay. So
for the initial three times I am failing
the call. I am failing the request and
after that three call I am sending the
success response.
So now what happen is my retry count is
four means total attempt is four. Out of
total attempt three are failing but I
want to make sure that my API gateway
retry. So at least it should uh total
there should be four calls. Okay. So
fourth call should get passed.
So now if you run this API gateway url
product / one what will happen is you
will see that fetch the product details
on fourth attempt so fet the product
detail on counter fourth attempt so
first three was fail actually so on
fourth it able to find so means our API
gateway properly did the retry and we
haven't written any code all we have
provided the configuration all the code
is already present
We just give which pre-existing
root filter we have to use and whatever
the config it has we have to just tell
assign the values whatever we want it
okay
also let's see circuit breaker how
circuit breaker we can uh make use of in
API gateway but if you have any doubt
with the circuit breaker kindly check it
out okay uh then it will get more
clarified like what is closed state,
what is open state, what is half open
state.
So first thing first in pom.xml
we have to add a dependency for the
resilience 4j.
So circuit breaker is used
like in within the resilience so
resilience 4j provide a circuit breaker
capability.
Okay. So that's why we need this
dependency. And if you have uh seen my
previous video of the fall tolerance,
you might know that hey shash retry also
functionalities provided by resilience
4j, right? Yes. But here in the API
gateway don't make use of resilience 4j.
It don't make use of resilience 4j. It
has their own uh logic buildup.
Okay.
So first thing first is we need the
resilience 4j dependency
now here in the application.properties
properties what we are doing it see this
again this is our product service root
and now we are writing the filter so
this is my first filter for the circuit
breaker I'm writing for this route root
zero filter zero what is the name
circuit breaker so you know right what
would be the class name circuit breaker
you can this will get appended
automatically gateway filter factory on
java
Okay. And now here if you see
the configuration it which uses it has
one name. So I am telling ARS dot name
and this name is what? This name is your
circuit breaker config. So if you have
seen this video you know that what are
the configurations we have to provide.
Okay. like how many uh like threshold
value what is the threshold value
and once it goes into the open state for
how much second it has to be in there
okay what
sliding window type it has to use all
this thing we have seen already in the
previous video so the same configuration
we provide and this is our circuit
breaker name you can say that just a
name we have given our circuit breaker
name. So in this name we provide this
value actually my circuit breaker name
whatever the name you want to give you
can provide uh give that name but use it
here. So what exactly it will do is our
filter
ultimately use the configurations
value from this
the here then whatever the uh circuit
breaker config name we have provided
here. So it will start reading the
values from here
and you if you also remember that it
there is also a fallback logic whenever
a request fails it also fall backs. So
that's why it has another field into its
config dot rfallback and we provide this
forward colon/
your it actually a path. So here if you
see I have written one controller inside
an API gateway itself. So this is a
controller I have given /f fallback and
written a service is temporarily unable
like how I want to handle. So the same
thing you have to give here that
fallback URI forward col/ means it's an
internal call means it is within API
gateway itself. There is no external
call to any microser. No, it's a
internal call. So that's why it just
forward col/ it's tell to the API
gateway it's an internal call.
/f fallback is the end point which it
has to invoke.
Okay.
So this is how circuit breaker happen
like so for testing what happened is the
same thing what I did previously in the
previous circuit breaker video. I did
not start the product micros service
server itself.
So I have given like threshold 50. 50%
is my threshold. Out of 10 calls if five
failed then means circuit should get
open. So that's what I did. I called
multiple times more than five times. So
threshold will get crossed. Okay. And
what would happen is you will see the
fallback message services temporarily
unavailable. And if you check the locks,
you will see that the transition state
transition happen from close to open.
Okay.
Now it will wait for 10 second in open
and then it will move back to
automatically
half open.
Okay.
So all the filters are already present.
Similarly for the rate limiter also the
exist filter already exists all we have
to use it like this
like how we are using. So provide a
filter name and this filter name would
be you can know that from the class you
can take out the prefix
and then if it required if it is using
some config just check out that config
like is they have any uh name fields
okay and those fields value we can
provide dynamically like this dot asks
dot field name and then value.
Now the last thing is okay Shange how to
write our custom root specific filter.
Now I have already seen how the
pre-existing
root filter works but how to write my
own custom root.
So very very simple. So here if you see
I have root see this one
I have given the name class name custom
root gateway filter factory. So you know
that in the pom uh not in the pom. So
this is our
application
dotproperties
not pom.xml.
So
whatever the filter what what's the
filter name would be this one custom
rate root gateway filter factor would
not come here it will automatically get
appended during mapping.
Okay. So I have created a class
annotated with component. I want to get
it managed through spring boot extend
abstract gateway filter factory. And see
I have provided one config. In this
class I have created one custom config
this class. I have created one custom
config class. So I have told that my
this
class which I'm writing it will use this
config and in this config I have so this
is just for testing purpose. So I have
just provided one field string country
that's all. So you know that now to fill
the value of this root zero filter
whatever the if is the fifth filter
let's say there are already filter zero
filter one filter two filter three
filter four. So this is the fifth filter
in the chain dot asks.
So for this
class
in this config which it use whatever the
field name would be I can use it country
and I can provide any value which I
wanted dynamically. So I put India.
Now what would happen is when this apply
will run. Okay. So here in this one I
can provide our pre-logic system.r print
element I whatever the pre-logic you
wanted you can use that and it has this
custom config
okay as an argument which we can use it
like this once the pre-logic is done
okay you can call the next filter in the
chain so I'm just calling chain dot
filter xchain so means next filter got
invoke and after that my post filter
logic
Okay. And that's all
done. If you run the application and hit
an API, you will see that my prefilter
logic, the value India which I provided
got printed and after that post filter
runs also. So this is how simple to
write a filter in it in API gateway.
Okay.
And using this filter only
we can do authentications.
We can do rate limiting. We can do
circuit breaker, retry, request,
response, transformation, monitoring,
logging, etc. Okay, just see your use
case. If your use case is like, hey, I
want to apply it for all the request
then go for global filter. If I have to
apply it to a specific request, go for
root specific filter.
Okay, I hope this makes sense and it
would be helpful in your interviews and
day-to-day work. But if you have any
doubt, let me know in the comment
section. We can discuss further. Bye.